Discuss the closure of Heinz
Wattie's, Greeks and McCain's food processing.
So, raise your hands to start
with. Expect
probably a little bit of a summary of what's happened,
and there's going to be a lot of questions, I assume.
Yeah. Thank you very much.
So
yeah, very nice to be here this morning.
I'm the small chair of the commission, Suzanne Stu, our Chief Executive.
Good morning.
And Andy Burgess, who's our GM of the infrastructure
branch. It's lovely to be with so many farmers.
I'll try and avoid talking about weather and tractors and
such,
and focus on Heinz Wattie and product
processing facilities. So I think
that we probably should start by saying we don't have particular insight into
either of these ones that you're interested in, but we can talk
about
factors that
make life difficult for firms like that.
And
I think we can talk about domestic factors, but also I think it
would be
relevant to look into the ownership structure,
and what was going on
in the corporate entities prior to those decisions
that were made. And on that point, I think we're all
aware that
multinational organizations have a kind of global portfolio
allocation process, that
depending on their capital structure, they may
choose to
engage in things that are profitable from a tax point of view,
like
management fees and so on out
of a country and licensing of brands and debt
levels and so on. So,
I don't know, I don't have any particular insight into what financial
stress these processes were under at the time they made these
decisions. But I do think it's probably relevant to
those decisions.
To the
other factors that have been raised,
one that's related to the costs of energy,
and
another that's potentially related to the operation of the
grocery sector. So we can answer questions about
those,
and help you think through both those matters.
Just on the grocery side of things, just which I think is,
I'm not sure there's a lot to be discovered
from there. I am aware that there was a
category review process that affected Heinz Wattie,
prior to the introduction of the Grocery Industry Competition Act.
So about the time when
the Commerce Commission was doing its market study into groceries,
there was a category review process, which is a common thing in
supermarkets, and sometimes that leads to
products being delisted. In fact, that's kind of
part of the purpose of category reviews is to decide which
products remain on the shelves and at what
cost to the supermarkets.
So,
that event, as my understanding is with Heinz Wattie,
that event happened about four years before they closed.
So it may have been a factor, but it wasn't
the immediate stressor. If it was a factor, it
was something that
from which the effects built up over time.
On the energy side,
it's
no secret that
wholesale energy prices were really, really high in
2024,
as a result of a combination of factors,
and that a number of processing operations,
not just food, but also
forestry processors and so on,
really struggled and indeed closed during that period as a result,
with high energy prices being pointed
to as a contributing factor.
So I think you probably can't rule that out
as a factor.
And
I suppose more than happy to talk about what's been
and being done in that sector
more recently to try and
moderate those prices and get things on a
much stronger track,
as with energy, any kind of
large
non-tradable
sector in New Zealand, industry reform and change is a slow
process and difficult one. But with clear
direction and
determination, better things can happen, and the commission's
very much involved
in those efforts. So I might just stop there, if that's all right.
Yeah.
Mr. Chair, and I'm going to take questions.
Yes. We'll go straight to Steve Abel.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you very much for coming in.
I wonder,
we've got a very strong submission from a number of
impacted parties, but one of the acknowledges from
Heretonga Hostings near is the
sort of system impact of losing processing capability
as it affects growers and that local Hawkes Bay economy.
And everyone trying to work out
what are reasonable interventions that
any government should consider to protect that processing
capability and recognize it as
strategic significance-
Mm
... for the whole economy and for food resilience.
Notwithstanding the right of companies to sell up,
are there
options that you consider are reasonable to stop
potentially anti-competitive behavior?
There's suggestions that the asset stripping of facility before it was
ever put on the market as a going concern may have undermined the
ability of a growers' cooperative
to make a successful bid on taking over the facility.
Mm.
And
what could
any given government do to
ensure that there's some
period of time within which
when a strategically significant facility such as
McCain's or Heinz Beanz is going to close,
that there's an option for
local buyers or buyers from anywhere, to be honest, to have a
crack at taking it over as a going concern.
Yeah, a really interesting set of issues in there.
And
I think what you're pointing to is the value of
optionality. I certainly endorse that.
And as to
whatever the owners did with
the internal plant,
that's a really interesting question. I don't know the facts of the matter.
But I have seen
in previous lives when I was working in private practice, I've
seen situations where companies
would rather take grinders
to their stainless steel than-
Yes
... than leave the plant fall into a competitor's hands.
So they're deliberately trying to destroy capacity, take it out of the economy
and specifically for,
well, they would say for pro-competitive reasons, but of course pro-competitive
being the thing that they
And there's certainly some evidence that that's what happened in the case of
McCain.
Right. So that kind of conduct is,
as I say, I
have seen that personally before in a previous life, and it's
always struck me as being something that's
pretty destructive and
all being in one company's interests,
maybe not in the interests of competition and the
wider economy. So I think that's a policy issue, really.
There's no
regulatory
tool, I don't think, that we could use to get at it.
Potentially if there was a case under the Commerce
Act under Section 36 or something like that,
we may be able to take action, but those things are slow processes,
and by the time you get started, everything's all in bits.
And so it's kind of too late. It's not really-
A good follow on, really.
It's-
Quick sup.
Yeah.
Just a quick sup.
Do you know if there's examples abroad where there are
legislative requirements, for example, for there to
be some time period within which a business that's going to be closed
or sold is available before such asset stripping can
occur?
That seems to be an obvious thing that could happen as a-
Yeah, I'm not aware of that, but we could do a bit of looking into that.
Thank you.
Yeah. I had a sup as well, which is
nearly identical issue, but different industry.
So I think this is wider than just what's happened in Hawke's Bay,
and just your
comment about it being a policy issue, yeah, it would be interesting to know what
sort of legislative options we could be looking at.
The case of Carter Holt Harvey in
the Nelson region closing up, even though it was profitable and there
being four interested buyers in the plant,
but two of which were
genuine capable buyers. And on
top of that, a situation where the region has significant windthrow of timber that
needs to be processed following
the 2024 floods. So there's a need to process the timber
at a profitable
plant, but decision made by the company
to consolidate in the North Island and
not
sell the plant. So a loss of over 100 jobs, and then the
timber being shipped rather than being processed in the region.
So, strategically, really problematic, really
anti-competitive. We're seeing this across
multiple parts of the manufacturing sector.
So I would just be really keen to know what policy and
legislative options you would think MPs could be looking at.
Because
the issue came up when that happened around Section 36, but again, too slow.
By the time you've gone through that process-
Yeah, it's a very slow process
...
everything's been sold up and scrapped, so.
Yeah. So
that's another interesting example.
The one I was thinking of occurred in the dairy processing sector.
So I think
as you're pointing out, these are issues that arise from
time to time in a number of different industrial sectors.
Probably is worth our while as a country thinking about how to react to them.
I would just caution, though, that
in some cases,
we do end up with excess capacity, and it's not a bad...
So you wouldn't want the default to be always you've got to
preserve the capacity. And I'm thinking here of,
for example, meat processing-
Yeah
As a result of all us people out there milking cows,
the flow of product through the meat works has dropped off a
lot and there's a whole lot of stranded capacity.
And there's a question about how you rationalize that capacity when it's
owned by a whole lot of different people.
And while it's all there, it's highly competitive
but
potentially a bit inefficient. So look, I'm
afraid I don't have an actual answer, but I do recognize the question that
you're asking. I think it kind of goes
both ways.
Yeah, because it just comes back to, doesn't it, when there's actually genuine
competitive need.
Yes.
Yeah.
So, Suze, you looked this up.
So I'm just wondering, is there any mechanism available
to protect sort of strategic assets in that respect?
In this case, the farmers clearly rallied
themselves pretty quickly and showed an intention to be able to
move forward and then
they were sort of hamstrung. But is there anything available to them or
to us to allow a strategic asset like that to be protected
or to give them the opportunity to-
They actually put in a bid.
Yeah, to put in.
Yeah. No, but yeah.
Because it was...
Yeah. Is there a pathway to do that?
Not to my knowledge, short of getting a court injunction, but you'd need
to have
a rationale for how this was going to play out in court more than anything.
So if you've got bad actors on the other side, there's really nothing you can do
about it?
It's pretty tough. Look, and I'll tell you what, we do see this in a
merger context as well. We see
similar kinds of commercial strategic game playing,
game playing in the formal sense,
as regards who knows what and when
things are happening. You see this play out in a number of different sectors
quite recently in merger cases we've had this year.
But the short answer is no, and I'm not sure how you'd
even get to that short of having a list of
things that
there were special requirements over or something of that sort, but I don't
know if-
Because reading the submission, some of the things that they proposed I don't think
are necessarily viable. Like
saying that they're competing with countries that can produce cheaper and what have
you, and suggesting proposing tariffs which is not going to happen, I don't
think. But this thing, this was one lever they had to
pull which just seemed really unfair that the carpet got ripped out.
Yeah.
But there's not really anything that you can do about it.
No, and as I said, in a merger context we've seen situations where there are
credible bidders and they really struggle to get
an opportunity.
And it
does go to strategic commercial conduct on the
part of the people who currently own the assets.
Now,
in
response to your question earlier,
has this been addressed anywhere around the world?
Not to my knowledge, but I'm more than happy to have a look at that
and see if we can throw you some advice on it.
We'll go to Mark Cameron, who's online.
Good morning, everyone. Nice to see you all.
I think the real question what we're asking to you good people,
is what is the role of government, really?
We appreciate, I just heard you mention court injunction.
That's an interesting dynamic in
so much that would be quite significant interference by
the judiciary. So I think the ultimate question is, what is the
role of government when strategic assets,
for whatever reasons, either economically fail or
by virtue of free market decide, to
Rachel's point, to condense or solidify in
strategic regions of the country based on market tensions.
So where do you think
the role of the Crown ultimately lands?
So you're really asking me a policy question on that one .
I know.
And I see you smiling, but really and truly, this is
where it lands.
It's a fair question,
and
I wouldn't be doing this job if I didn't think that regulators could add
value. I
do think we can.
And
also we do take
that kind of view
on some things, for example, cement recently.
Mm-hmm.
But that's kind of an ad hoc
response to a particular situation, and I suppose
what I would
advocate would be something of
if we think this is an issue, that something a little systematic
that could be thought through in advance and you go, "Oh, well, what
are the sorts of situations in which
we want..." Our job is to promote competition, so all of this is
the
same direction that you folk are all going in here.
You're wanting to preserve
the opportunity for more competition by using
existing assets that we've already got.
So fully endorse that as an objective.
The mechanism is the hard part, and so I
don't disagree.
No, I appreciate that. I know it was a fickle question, but
that I say that, and I'm glad that you
offered spoke the way you did. We appreciate it's our
role to do this. But at what point does the Crown interfere in
private enterprise is the real question.
Mm-hmm. Yeah.
Yes.
Very good. Thank you
Have you done any
work on the
margins that the
growers get versus what the products are sold for?
I mean, um-
Oh,
no, not specifically.
We,
no-
It's a submission, isn't it?
Right.
We, we, we currently got before us a merger of, um,
vegetable wholesalers.
Mm.
Um, and, and we're working through that quite 'cause it's quite, quite a tricky,
uh, matter actually 'cause the whole lot of huge
variety and, and it, and, and competitive conditions are
different in different parts of the country, so that's a difficult matter.
But we're, we're, we're attacking that from a, um, sort of more principles,
um, competitive basis by looking at conditions in each part of
the country. We have not done that, that work,
no.
Yeah. Well, it's, it's interesting.
I mean, a loaf of bread is about $4.50 at the moment.
Probably about
4 or 500 grams of flour in it.
The gr- the, the grower gets 40 cents a
kilogram for wheat, near enough.
So, 20 cents of that $4.50 goes to the grower.
Mm.
It's, it's, um, really interesting to see 'cause in
Canterbury there's a lot of growers up in sticks
changing land use.
That's right.
Yeah.
They cannot make it work.
Mm-hmm.
No.
And yet,
um, they point to the fact that the product that's
been made is, um, what?
200 times or whatever.
Yeah.
Mm.
No, and, and I mean, as a, as a farmer,
you're sort of painfully aware of the difference between gate prices and
retail prices. Um, it, it's massive and,
and that's why I think, you know, the, the out- out task and, and the one that
you're focusing on here, which is promoting competition in the processing layer,
um, is super important because the more competitive...
We see this in the meat industry now.
It's more competitive because there's more capacity and more f- more individual
players, um, and so therefore gate prices are higher.
It's really, really obvious, and you can see it in, in the US in particular where
meat-
100%
... packaging is very concentrated.
Mm.
'Cause it seems to me that there's a tension between that, uh,
competitive principle to drive down consumer value
and the farmer being
sort of paradoxically the, the one that gets the worst return even though they're
the most essential to the product existing.
And, and
the, the question that seems to come from certainly growers recently that I've
talked to is the, the question of what the markups are-
Yeah
... at the retail level. Whether they're reasonable.
Transparency around what they're being told.
Yep.
Um, so and so down the road has sold their head of broccoli for,
versus what, you know, what, what they think it should be
reasonably worth given what it's retailing for in that week.
So-
And so that kind of transparency on the, um,
those who have the
price brokering power because of their scale, i.e.
the supermarkets-
Yeah.
Mm
... um, versus, uh, you know, the grower just has to take what they're
offered really.
Yeah. So there's a, there's an emerging, um, uh,
area of antitrust law that looks at
that, and that's like-
Yeah
... B2B transactions. Um, New Zealand's, you know, got a
little way to go to get up to an international frontier in there, but we're, we're
sort of working on that.
Uh, I'd say one other thing, though, um, a bit more generally about
this, you know, you kind of characterize w- we want, we want strong
competition right throughout the sector so the consumer gets the lowest price and
there's an element of truth in that, but it's not, it's not entirely abs-
absolutely accurate. You look at the way we looked at the North
South Foodstuffs merger.
Mm.
Our, our big concern there, uh, one of our big concerns
there was that this was gonna be a three to two merger in
the acquisition of groceries, so it was gonna, it was gonna concentrate
the purchasing sector,
uh, which was be to the detriment of the food suppliers.
Mm.
Who would include growers and, and, and, and other manufacturers like Heinz,
Motty and, and, and the like. So we see that, we, we see that
balancing of market power as, um, as
important for competition.
Mm.
Um, it's not always
necessarily the lowest price. Um, it's
you need, you need balanced competition, right?
No- nobody wants to watch
me being thrashed at tennis by, um, Serena Williams.
It's not, not competition.
It's, it's a kind of... So that balancing of market power we think is
quite important.
Yeah. Interesting. So-
Oh, I'll just say the other implication, which is not really relevant, but is the,
the impact it has on the actual model of farming because some people use those,
growing those legumes to sort of help, it fixes nitrogen or whatever-
Mm
... so they don't need to use as much fertilizer.
So like it's part of the-
Mm
... part of the rotational planning for their farms.
Absolutely.
So if you suddenly have to change to another crop or do something different, it can
have an impact-
Well, they're just gonna switch to seed and bean
... on the environment and on your farming model. Yeah.
Or use more urea. Yeah.
And they can re- grow grass in between or whatever. Yeah.
Yeah.
So it's-
No, I totally get you
... it has a trickle-down effect.
It does. It really does.
Yeah.
It, it... Right across the ecosystem and the way you started off with the, with
the, you know, the, the workers and growers and around
Hawitonga, you know, that's, that's a big impact there.
Mm.
Huge. Yeah, so that's where you sort of need to, I guess as a any
subsequent government needs to get into that space of looking at the bigger
picture and working out what's an appropriate intervention There's the
consequences down the track, and it's very hard to bring it back once you've lost
the facility.
Yeah, and it needs to be done in a
forward-looking, principled kind of way, recognizing it could go either way in
particular circumstances.
Yeah. Well, it just did seem unconscionable in this situation that it was that the
growers motivated themselves really quickly.
They worked out that, did a study of the model, thought that it was sort of
top-heavy and that they could reduce some costs and make it more efficient-
Mm-hmm
... in terms of the
freezer space, in particular. There were all sorts of things that they'd done, the
research, and then it just got ripped out from under them.
Mm-hmm.
So, maybe another question I've got is around the home brand stuff,
where-
Oh, yeah
... you've got
the pressure to provide home brand from the suppliers.
Mm-hmm.
And then their branded product, which is on the same shelves.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
And, in discussion with different suppliers,
that's basically saying that they're
subsidizing
their own product-
Mm
... because they're forced to sell the home brand stuff's basically
under-
Mm
... cost of production.
Mm-hmm.
And that's just to get shelf space.
So if you don't supply it, you won't have shelf space.
So
have you done any research into that model?
This is a fairly big issue in the grocery sector.
And I'm sure you understand how the
major retailers do this.
Yeah.
They put out tenders for the
lowest price you can give me to supply me with a product that looks like this, and
then that becomes my own brand.
In the process, I've learned about how much it costs to produce that.
So when somebody comes along with a branded product that looks much the same, I
already know quite a lot about your cost structure.
That helps me in my negotiations.
And then I get to choose where those sit on the shelf and at
what price points.
So
we recognize it's an issue. We recognize that it
squeezes growers and producers.
We don't have an answer for it yet.
Yeah. Just to follow up on that is, is there something
wrong with the system, do you think, where
you can sell products as your own when you don't grow them,
manufacture them,
you're just selling them?
So you think
because they've got so much power-
Mm
... the supermarkets can
demand that a home brand type product be sold.
I know the consumers like it because it's cheaper, but at the end of the day, it's
squeezing growers out.
Yeah. I think I'd just go back to the point that
we really want more retail competition for groceries.
I speak for that as well, Steve. You got three
parties happening to be at the table now and not Mark, but that
have all proposed some sort of intervention in the supermarkets of different kinds,
like anti-competitive or breaking up the duopoly in different
ways.
Do you think we're at a stage now with the challenges around the cost of food,
but also potentially,
the way the dominance and the power of the retailer in terms of the
supermarkets, that it is appropriate for us to have those sorts of interventions?
Yeah, I can't obviously comment on
these specific policies.
No.
Can't ask him for a political answer.
I'm trying to not ask for a political answer.
I'm trying to ask for a general principle of-
I think it's-
... are we at a stage where it's, we're in the right track to be looking at that?
The commission's on record, as you know, for several years now, as saying
that we think that the structure of the grocery
retailing sector
needs to be improved.
Yeah.
And we've got a set of tools that are kind of behavioral regulation tools that were
given to us a few years ago that we're using to try
and push that.
Mm-hmm.
And so that's one way we can carry on down that road.
We know that, and we've said this publicly, that it's a long, slow road.
Mm-hmm.
And I know it annoys the
supermarkets and imposes costs on them and
so on.
That's the current policy.
And it will, I think it would
actually
improve com- there are some signs that it has sort of
worked. Some people have used the wholesale regime to get a bit of
scale and then go direct and now they're
retailing in competition with Pack and Save nationwide.
There's Paddock to Pantry is doing that on a delivery basis.
So
that kind of process can work-
Mm-hmm
... but it's a pretty long, slow process.
And ultimately, the aim is to change the structure, by
which I mean there's more retailers-
Yeah
... more diverse retailers.
Thank you very much. We've come to time.
Lovely.
Appreciate you coming in this morning.
Thank you.
That's great.